you might think that you don't need to learn
tracking but tracking is a key concept you
must know when you start to learn GrandMA3 programming understanding tracking helps you
a lot in the future when you start making real
GrandMA3 shows in this episode of our GrandMA3
tutorial series i'll try to explain what
GrandMA3 tracking is where it comes from
and why it's so important to learn i'll show you
some examples of how to use it and i'll show you
something very important like merging values into
your GrandMA3 show but equally important how you
can remove values again so tracking stays intact
before we start i'll try to explain what tracking
is and why it's so important GrandMA3 tracking
is not something that is unique to GrandMA3
or to GrandMA almost every lighting console
uses tracking in one way or the other so the
concept of tracking is something you can use in
most lighting programming not just products from
MA lighting tracking on GrandMA3 is something
that was developed back in the day when you had to
move large physical faders on a dimmer rack then
the lighting crew was handed a cue sheet with all
the changes for a set of faders which was written
down but each handle would only register if there
was a change if there were no change, the fader
would track the value from the previous cue so
the core concept of tracking is basically only
to record changes that means that your lighting
fixtures will not need any new information if
you don't want them to do something different,
than they are already doing this basically means
that if you turn on a fixture in cue 1 of a GrandMA3
sequence it'll stay on until you tell it to do
something else let me demonstrate as you can see
i prepared a little new show for us here with
a bunch of mega points in it so let's start by
making a sequence we take all our mega points we
turn them on maybe we put them into a position
and we store that into a cue so now we have
one cue with some mega points on and they are
all turned on in a position let's just just record
some empty cues so we say store cue 2 through 10
and we just recorded 9 extra cues and if we
clear the programmer right here like we did
now and we can go the cue we can see in cue 1
all the mega points are on everything is good so
when i go into the next cue the mega points are
still on and that's because they are tracking the
values and there will there's no change so that's
why they are they are staying in the exact same
position and with the dimmers on - to better have
an understanding of what is happening you can
turn on the track sheet up here so if you turn on
the track sheet it's going to register what every
fixture is doing in each cue as you can see
right now it's in pain and tilt is in position 2.1
which is down here position 2.1 and if we
scroll over here you can probably find the
dimmer values yeah the demo values are right
here so for fixture one the dimmers are at
full and and and so on all the way up to
the other ones so that is basically tracking
it's gonna stay in the exact same position as you
put it in in the first cue unless you tell it to
do something different so what happens if you give
it some different information in cue 5 for instance?
so let's just do that with our dimmers let's
scroll down so we can see all our dimmer
values down here here we go if we select all our
mega points again and we set the intensity to 50
and maybe we store that in cue number 5
and we merge it in you can see now it's stored
at cue number five and if we find our dimmer
position again right here you can see it changed
from 100 down to 50 percent so now our cue 10
which we are currently in is still at 50 percent
so if we go through it's 100 percent then it
goes to 50 and then it stays at 50 percent all the
way down to cue 10 so that's basically what another
example of tracking you have our position oh sorry
our dimmer value at 100 it tracks through to cue
number 4 in cue 5 we give it a change and then it
tracks that value all the way to the end of the
cue list unless we give it another information
in a minute i'll show you what you can do if you
only want to record a new value in cue 5 and after
that you must go back to what it was doing in
the previous cue - but before that be sure to
hit the like button if you get anything out of
this video that will help the video spread to
more people on youtube and please subscribe to
the channel and click the little bell icon if
you want to be notified next time i upload a new
video but let's continue we are back in our little
demo show file here we have our cue 5 let's just take
all our mega points say 100 let's store that in cue 5
and let's remove the values again so right now we
are back into our tracking here we still have a
100 all the way down so let's say once again we
take all our mega points we put them at 50 and
we want to store this change in cue 5 but only in
cue 5 in cue 6 and so on it's going to go back to 100
we can do that really really easy we can say store
cue 5 enter and then you can merge it in but check
this little box called "Cue Only" this is going to set
the value for cue number 5 to the value we just put
in 50 and then in the next cue it's going to
go back to what it was doing before so if we say
"Cue Only" merge you can see it stored a value
of 50 in cue 6 and it also stored a percentage of
100 in cue number 6 and that's because
this is what it was doing in the previous cue
this is a brilliant function "Cue Only" and i
use it myself all the time it's it's it's going
to make you really really fast when you when you
do some changes if you for instance are doing a
concert and and you have a very short cue with
a lot of strobes happening or whatever you can do
it like this it's going to turn everything else
off do the strobes and go back to what it was
doing before so this is really good for for bump
cues - but you have to be careful with tracking
because it can unintentionally change something
in a later cue that you don't want to change
therefore you can block a cue sometimes you
don't want the GrandMA3 to track your values
through a certain cue that could be if you go
from act number 1 in a theater performance to act
number 2 and all the lighting is going to change
and you want to make sure that that it stays
exactly the same or it could be if you are doing a
rock concert and you go from one song to the next
you want to make sure that nothing nothing tracks
through from song number one into song number two
on the GrandMA3 you can block a cue so
nothing tracks through and that guards you from
accidentally changing something in a later cue
and as i said before there's two ways of doing
this let me just show you the first one as you
can see i just made a few changes to our view here
our sequence up here still has some information in
cue number one so if i go cue number one you can
still see exactly the same information let's go
into cue number seven we want to block cue number
seven but we want to make sure that nothing tracks
truth so we want to make sure that everything in
cue 7 is simply all our moving lights with a hard
value with no no lights on so we if we start by
turning off everything our sequence in this case
we clear the programmer and we want to select
all our fixtures and we want to make sure that
we select all our fixtures so we say 1 through
10 000 or the highest number of your fixture i
just want to show you that you can simply say
one through and then a very very high number
it's going to select everything so if i press
enter now you can see it selected all my mega
points and if i had hundreds of fixtures here
it would select everything from one to fixture 10
000. so now i've selected everything but i haven't
selected any values here but the GrandMA3 if
you press "Please" twice it's going to activate
each and every parameter as you can see here in
our mega points in this case but if you selected
a million fixtures it's going to select all the
parameters in all the fixtures not a million but
but close i want to store this into cue 7 so if
i say store cue 7 please and it's going to ask
us what to do and i just want to merge it in
as you can see now everything changed here so
we just recorded a value for our dimmers which is
at zero because everything is turned off right now
and if we clear this right now and we go back into
cue number one we had here down into cue number
five and now we go into cue number 7 and
everything turns off and goes back to a default
value that's the first way or the simple way and
the old way of building a block cue another way
of making a block cue is basically asking the
GrandMA3 to help you as you can see right
now once again everything is on back to our first
cue everything tracks through all our cue lists
right here and if we want to block this cue
you can simply just write in the command line
if we just select our command line right here
we can say block cue 7 for instance and as you
can see now it recorded hard values once again for
everything in our in our cue list here everything
that is active so it's kind of a different
way of doing it this is only going to block
the values that are in our cue list right
now so if you suddenly make a change to a
something that is not recorded here maybe you
do a change to a color let's just try to do that
let's select all our mega points then select the
red color and then store that into cue number one
like this and we merge it in let's see what
happens down here if it it doesn't block you
can see here if you introduce a new parameter it's
gonna track all the way through so it's not the
same but it's it's kind of helpful you can still
block a cube but if you want to make absolutely
certain that everything is blocked you have to
use the first technique i told you with selecting
your fixtures from one through to your highest
number next up i'll show you two ways of removing
unnecessary values in your GrandMA3 show because
the GrandMA3 console can help you in removing
those values that are unnecessary for your show
it can basically clean up your programming for you
but first let's remove a value because it's not
enough just to give a fixture a new value maybe
you want to change your fixture from 50 back up
to 100 percent like it was in the previous cue
and in this case it's a lot easier to remove the
current value instead of giving it a new value
that'll it's going to keep the tracking
intact but before i show you that let me
remind you to leave a comment if you have
any questions to this video i would love
to help you if you get stuck in something
or if you have something else on your mind
receiving comments is really nice and that lets
me know a little bit more about who is watching
the videos and what changes i need to make in the
future and check out the links in the description
if you want to look at some real GrandMA3
hardware here you can look at some different
models and read a bit more about each model so
let's get back into it we can manually remove
values from the GrandMA3 sequence i have made a
cue list with 10 cues in cue 5 or maybe we could just
continue where we left off we recorded some color
information if you remember right here maybe we
want to get rid of the color information again so
what we can do we clear our programmer we select
all our mega points and we know we want to get
rid of the color so we need to activate the color
parameters as you can see right now nothing is
active over here if i select our color preset
you can now see that the values for RG and B
are active when you record remove something
it's only going to remove the active values when
you do the removing process so i want to keep all
my dimmer information and i want to keep my position
information i just want to get rid of my color
information and you do that simply as we just did
select all the colors select the color parameters
make sure they're active and make sure that
nothing else is active because that's going
to get removed as well so right now we only
have our color active if we say store cue
1 enter and it's going to ask us do you want
to override do you want to merge do you want
to remove release or cancel i want to remove
so if i press remove you can see all the color
information disappeared but everything else
is still there this is how you remove and
basically if you want to remove everything
let's just uh try that we clear everything
we select all our mega points and we want to get
rid of them in cue 7 so we as i showed you before
select them press enter enter that selects all
the parameters and then we once again say store
cue 7 enter and we say remove and all the values
for all the fixtures are gone and now it's
tracking through cue number 7 so this is how
you remove you can also let the grandma3 unblock
a cue for you when you use the unblock function
on a GrandMA3 sequence the console automatically
goes through each and every cue in the selected
sequence and removes all the values that are
unnecessary that means that the GrandMA3 might
remove a lot of values but the output will remain
the same let me show you once again we are back in
our sequence as you can see here i stored a lot of
unnecessary information this one up here is a
hard value this is cue 1 so we need this hard value
this one this one and this one is represented
in white is also hard values but they're not
really necessary because it's already been told
to be at a hundred percent in cue number 1
down here we change it to fifty percent so this
is a necessary value but once again we stored the
same information in cue number 6 and that
is unnecessary information this one again is
necessary because we change from 50 to 100 percent
on our dimmer and again it's unnecessary values
down here so what we can do is unblock this
entire cue list or sequence so we say unblock
cue 1 through which means it starts at cue 1 and it
goes all the way through all the cue so if you
have 100 cues it's going to go through all of them
in this case we want to go through the entire cue
list but you probably wouldn't want to do that on
the normal circumstances but if you look up here
what is happening right now i say enter and as you
can see it changed the output is still the same
nothing happened to the output but now it's a hard
value up here it tracks the values here we change
it in cue 5 it tracks it in cue 6 we change it again in
cue 7 and it tracks all the way down to cue number
10. this is how you unblock a cue - i hope this video
gives you a better understanding of GrandMA3
tracking and why it's so important once you
learn how it works you can start to appreciate
the functionality of GrandMA3 tracking
and it can really help you as a GrandMA3
programmer in the future if you want to know more
about working with GrandMA3 consoles check
out this next video where i'll show you even more
tips and tricks you need as a GrandMA3 programmer
i hope you will consider liking the
video and subscribing to the channel
and if you do i'll see you in the next video
but until then happy GrandMA3 programming